[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is the shorter note on cetanā.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cetanā, properly speaking, is intentional intention, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: will or volition.
[SPEAKER_01]: The word intention, in its normal, looser meaning, will include these, and it's the best translation for cetanā.
So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a little wordy here, obviously, with the idea of, like, intention, you know, kind of containing both of those things, like, intentions and wills.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you speak briefly about, like, what is... Well, the thing is, you start with intention, you start with cetanā.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will need to reverse engineer it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will need to discern within that the subtle forms of intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That are the necessary basis for intentional intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to, again, not fall into the assumption of the external view, whereby you can sort of visualize the intention, and then that intention gets doubled, so it becomes intentional intention, and that's how you act.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You act, and through that action, you can discern that you acted in a certain manner, because you had given options.
[SPEAKER_00]: And given options, given possibilities, arisen implications of... within the arisen experience, those implications are already intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're already intentional.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you choose to attend certain intentions on account of other intentions that are equally given.
[SPEAKER_00]: And based on what you've been choosing to attend, you end up intentionally intending further and acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would say, you don't attend to unwholesome, you attend to wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't give
[SPEAKER_00]: improper attention to phenomena, because it will bring unwholesome to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no say in the manifestation of phenomena, but you do have a say in choosing to attend things based on sensuality, things based on ill will, things based on delusion and distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's within the the given, the basis of possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, within anything, you can exercise restraint, or you can exercise indulgence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's entirely up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in that middle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in trying to get rid of things or overly explain them or define how they came to be in what fraction of nanosecond.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's relevant is, halfway up in that middle, whether you're carelessly attending to it, carelessly giving rise to more sensuality on account of choosing to attend out of sensuality in the first place, and so on, or whether you're avoiding, whether you're saying, no, this is careless, this is sensual, and then you attend the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by attending the opposite, the sensuality ceases, the ill-will ceases, the distraction disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the encyclopedia article that he quotes in the last paragraph, there's one thing I wanted to bring up.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says that, eh... To be conscious of something is no empty having of that something in consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each phenomenon has its own intentional structure, which analysis shows to be an ever-widening system of individually intentional, intentionally related components.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's brought up here in this phenomenological approach is the idea of there being structures of experience of things... Yeah, that's what we just said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's not wrong to describe it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's certainly not, eh... it's not, eh... what the Buddha would call opanaiko.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something that would lead you to the... to the further understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a description that provided you with information.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it won't lead you to further understanding, because it's... it's based on external point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're describing this... this complex, eh... structure of intentionality, and it is accurate way to sort of describe it, but it... it does not represent how it's being lived and seen, which is what comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can only step outside of that structure, in your abstraction, and provide a pleasing and accurate description, but it's still a description, as in explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still, it's still the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumes the external point of view of that structure, which you cannot step outside of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I meant when I said you have to actually look through what you have, which is your intentional action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that, you start discerning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within the arisen enduring phenomena of of possibilities to act, possibilities to make choice, you realize that how you're making choices by choosing to attend this, on account of this, and both of which are given.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of these possibilities are given within the choices that you've been making.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you start making wholesome at the expense of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the... talking about, describing the structure as the... as the phenomenology does, it's... it's accurate for a Putujana point of view, but it's certainly not something that can lead him out of the state of being Putujana, because he keeps assuming this point of view, which means he tacitly keeps assuming the place for that gratuitous sense of self, atavāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: Moving on to the last paragraph, he writes, we must also consider the matter of the difference of emphasis or weight possessed by various possible aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Though each alternative to the actual aspect is possible, they are not all equally probable or potential, and some stand out more prominently than others.
[SPEAKER_01]: The emphasized aspect may, of course, be the actual aspect as a negative of all the possible aspects, and this will tend to preserve the actual state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is attention, manasikāra, in its simplest terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: It may be described as a direction of emphasis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was just gonna say, emphasis is that attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choosing to emphasize something means it has to be done at the expense of something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't emphasize everything equally, because then there is no emphasis at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why the... the attention is like the core, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is one of the reasons for arising of the right view, the right attention and the right utterance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... you can't... you can't change things and make them only appear with wholesome options and wholesome possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just beyond your reach.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you can do is stop attending them wrongly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop attending them as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop attending them with desire and lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop attending them on the views of sensuality and greed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that that weight that he talks about, it's the weight that you would be responsible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a weight of a habit, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: There'll be a coarser example of it, but it's the extension of the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you've been engaging in certain
[SPEAKER_00]: You act, you develop a habit, as in you develop a certain pressure that's exercised on you that you can't say no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just have to do these habits now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are fully responsible for generating that pressure, that weight that's now oppressing you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And fundamentally, that's the principle of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep assuming the ownership of it, then the life becomes a burden, becomes something that it's weighing on you, with all its infinite possibilities, that you kind of implicitly feel are not in your control, and they're terrifying, yet you cannot help but be pressured into that ownership and sense of control of it, that you're fully responsible for, by giving in to desire and lust in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_00]: You accumulate the weight of various significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's hard to say no to centrality, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because it's fundamentally contains all that weight instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you've been engaging with it for so long that you built it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's why it is also possible to undo it and overcome it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop engaging in the acts
[SPEAKER_00]: That perpetuates, that maintains and adds more of that weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we're talking about a burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the things you do, you keep accumulating burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can't stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, it's true, you might be too pressured by the habits, but you're responsible for the habits behind that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you just start gradually developing strength in terms of restraint, that emphasis... well, you create a broader perspective from which you can choose to emphasize things.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're fully absorbed with just gratification of your senses, acting upon your will and so on, yeah, you're just driven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your emphasis is driven by the weight that you've been accumulating and maintaining through careless attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you change that, you start attending things carefully, you stop feeding that pressure, and by not feeding the pressure, you actually develop a greater perspective then.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it becomes easier to shift the emphasis on wholesome at the expense of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would say the restraint, the sīla, the virtue needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is simply... it's not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, is the structure of both careful and uncareful attention fundamentally the same as he's describing here?
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally the same?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like he's describing... Well, it's along the same lines, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's either or.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is it then that distinguishes the careful attention, at least, I guess you could maybe call it intention?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's whether it's rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which are the things, which were the weights, which were the pressures, that should not be there, but there is no first point before which they weren't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they always have been there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you start... once you stop feeding them, and once you understand them, they fade and they cannot return, because there is actually no room for that type of weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is from the last footnote, footnote F. Though there is intention, cetanā, both simple and reflexive, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: volition, in the arahant's experience, there is no craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, there is, and there is not, intention of the arahant, just as there is, and there is not, consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no consciousness of intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving, however, is a gratuitous, though beginningless, parasite on the intentional structure described here, and its necessity is not to be deduced from the necessity of intention in all experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intention does not imply craving, a hard thing to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, parasite needs its host.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there cannot be craving without intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there can be intention without a craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that craving is that, that, that weight that has been beginninglessly perpetuated in regard to one's intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving of sensuality, obviously the most notable one.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense desires, craving for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of those things, that type of weight, as a criteria for your choice, as in, like, there's something painful, my weight of that criteria is avoid the pain, and that's my default action.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can be undone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what happens to an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he doesn't undo the agreeable or disagreeable feelings, but he undoes the craving in regard to them, which is then means, yeah, he... From the point of view of Putujana, arahant has no feelings then.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the point of view of Putujana, which is, his only intention that he can know is the intention affected by craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he was to discern how can arahant have an intention without craving, well, he would be at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, from the point of view of Putujana, arahant doesn't have intentions, doesn't have consciousness, doesn't have anything, because for Putujana, intentions, consciousness, feelings are the things that are fully weighted by that... by that pressure of craving and unwholesomeness.